<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>If you want to build a ship on Hamilton Lima</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/</link><description>Recent content in If you want to build a ship on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 12:56:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hamiltonlima.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Guiding Principles for Cleaner Code: YAGNI, KISS, SOLID, and Beyond</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/guiding-principles-for-cleaner-code-yagni-kiss-solid-and-beyond/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 12:56:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/guiding-principles-for-cleaner-code-yagni-kiss-solid-and-beyond/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Any fool can write code that a computer can understand. Good programmers write code that humans can understand.&amp;rdquo; - Martin Fowler source
When you start your coding journey, the natural instinct is to write instructions as if you&amp;rsquo;re talking to a person: &amp;ldquo;Hey computer, grab some eggs, butter, and flour, and let&amp;rsquo;s bake a cake.&amp;rdquo; Procedural it is—instruction after instruction, right? It seems easy to understand, but it’s actually not 😊.</description></item><item><title>Exploring NestJS: A Personal Journey and Key Insights</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/exploring-nestjs-a-personal-journey-and-key-insights/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 21:31:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/exploring-nestjs-a-personal-journey-and-key-insights/</guid><description>Time flies! It feels like just yesterday when Qi Chen introduced NestJS as our backend technology at Mindbeacon back in 2019. It was a perfect match for Angular—similar coding styles, dependency injection, plenty of decorators, and loads of CLI options. Today, NestJS (not to be confused with its cousin, Next.js) can do so much more: scheduling, support for RabbitMQ, Kafka, Redis, WebSockets, and the list goes on.
I might be a bit biased, having used it for the past five years, but sometimes it feels like I&amp;rsquo;ve not just used it—I&amp;rsquo;ve pushed it to its limits!</description></item><item><title>A love letter to ourselves</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/love-letter-to-ourselves/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/love-letter-to-ourselves/</guid><description>In the fast-paced world we live in, stress often feels like an unwelcome companion. But what if we had a tool to navigate through it? A process can serve as just that—an anchor in the storm, a love letter from our rational self to our stressed self.
A well-defined process is like having a map. It reduces decision fatigue by laying out clear steps, helping us focus on one task at a time.</description></item><item><title>Daily Standups with a Twist: Ideas to Encourage Team Autonomy</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 01:47:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</guid><description>We are social animals and want to be part of a tribe, feel accepted, useful, and so on. Combine that with the fact that working remotely is incredibly convenient and productive—there&amp;rsquo;s no commuting downtime. (By the way, I’m not talking to those of you who join meetings while driving. Please don&amp;rsquo;t do that!) So, how do we achieve collaboration and a sense of belonging in a remote setting? I don&amp;rsquo;t have all the answers, but I can share some of the experiences and lessons we learned while building Playspace.</description></item><item><title>Happy blue t-shirt day</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/happy-blue-tshirt-day/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 08:51:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/happy-blue-tshirt-day/</guid><description>During the craziness of COVID, many people started visiting places in their minds where, as a Theologist, I already enjoy frequent flyer status. These are not all dark places; there are certainly gray ones, and a few dark places as well. Mostly, they are places inside your head with dust and very low circulation. I am talking about questions on life and death, the meaning of our existence, and similar questions that are not usually part of lunch talk.</description></item><item><title>Confirm new user email with Cypress and MailHog</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 09:09:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</guid><description>I really like Cypress, The tool is interactive, very developer friendly even if you don&amp;rsquo;t plan to have a fully automated test suite, it really can save time automating tasks like, fill some forms, repeat some tasks, reproduce bugs, create new users&amp;hellip; create new USERS&amp;hellip; oh wait CREATE NEW USERS, how on earth I will validate the user email?
So many options There are some posssibilities
Pay some email API services, oh GMAIL why you don&amp;rsquo;t have it?</description></item><item><title>Avoid insanity when handling errors with Chai</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-insanity-when-handling-errors-with-chai/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jul 2021 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-insanity-when-handling-errors-with-chai/</guid><description>If you ever played Farcry3 for sure you will remember the guy in the picture, if you never hear about him, Take a look on this video, The definition of insanity - Far Cry 3.
While coding some unit tests for the SmallFlatWorld server, I got myself in a very interesting situation, where my old Java memories guided me to implement a test in a specific way, while some documentation was pointing in another direction&amp;hellip; Well Vaas has a point, repeating the same thing over and over and expecting the same results it&amp;rsquo;s kinda insane.</description></item><item><title>Image Processing with Ionic</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/image-processing-with-ionic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 12:52:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/image-processing-with-ionic/</guid><description>One of these days at the office at the end of an inspiring meeting we found ourselves stuck. Image some experienced Software Engineers trying to find a proper angle to make a picture. That&amp;rsquo;s right trying to find an angle, and the best we could do was this. Most of the meeting room walls are made of glass, it&amp;rsquo;s an invitation to make notes, to draw, but how to make pictures of it so we can save as &amp;ldquo;documentation&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Using Redis Publish and Subscribe</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/using-redis-publish-and-subscribe/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 01:01:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/using-redis-publish-and-subscribe/</guid><description>There is this game called Robolucha where you code your robots to fight in a virtual arena. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this project for some years and last year decided to rewrite everything, mainly for the sake of technical exploration and this post share challenges using Redis Publish and subscribe.
Proving the concept Before I start to hit the keyboard to refactor MatchStatePublisher to send match states to Redis, I had some homework to do.</description></item><item><title>Virtualbox with static and dynamic IP</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/virtualbox-with-static-and-dynamic-ip/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 14:49:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/virtualbox-with-static-and-dynamic-ip/</guid><description>While installing docker on my windows 10 machine I found that Docker for Windows requires 64-bit Windows 10 Pro with Hyper-V available, what? omg, I was expecting something simple&amp;hellip; but NISBEIP, let&amp;rsquo;s move on. Tried to use the Docker Toolbox that didn&amp;rsquo;t work as smooth as I expected. After some hours banging my head against the wall I decided to create a Linux Virtual Machine using Virtualbox and use docker from there.</description></item></channel></rss>