<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hamilton Lima</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/</link><description>Recent content on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 12:52:49 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hamiltonlima.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Image Processing with Ionic</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/image-processing-with-ionic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 12:52:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/image-processing-with-ionic/</guid><description>One of these days at the office at the end of an inspiring meeting we found ourselves stuck. Image some experienced Software Engineers trying to find a proper angle to make a picture. That&amp;rsquo;s right trying to find an angle, and the best we could do was this. Most of the meeting room walls are made of glass, it&amp;rsquo;s an invitation to make notes, to draw, but how to make pictures of it so we can save as &amp;ldquo;documentation&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Using Redis Publish and Subscribe</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/using-redis-publish-and-subscribe/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 01:01:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/using-redis-publish-and-subscribe/</guid><description>There is this game called Robolucha where you code your robots to fight in a virtual arena. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this project for some years and last year decided to rewrite everything, mainly for the sake of technical exploration and this post share challenges using Redis Publish and subscribe.
Proving the concept Before I start to hit the keyboard to refactor MatchStatePublisher to send match states to Redis, I had some homework to do.</description></item><item><title>Virtualbox with static and dynamic IP</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/virtualbox-with-static-and-dynamic-ip/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 14:49:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/virtualbox-with-static-and-dynamic-ip/</guid><description>While installing docker on my windows 10 machine I found that Docker for Windows requires 64-bit Windows 10 Pro with Hyper-V available, what? omg, I was expecting something simple&amp;hellip; but NISBEIP, let&amp;rsquo;s move on. Tried to use the Docker Toolbox that didn&amp;rsquo;t work as smooth as I expected. After some hours banging my head against the wall I decided to create a Linux Virtual Machine using Virtualbox and use docker from there.</description></item><item><title>From counters to promises a javascript journey</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/from-counters-to-promises-a-javascript-journey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 13:21:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/from-counters-to-promises-a-javascript-journey/</guid><description>Beauty always promises, but never gives anything. Simone Weil
Unlike beauty, javascript promises are faithful, and will be fulfilled&amp;hellip; unless someone rejects it :) If you ever need to load images using javascript or did anything that needs to wait until something is done, you probably used a promise, maybe even without noticing. I see Promises as a nice way to simplify the callback hell, but don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled, the callbacks are still there, they are only organized in a more simpler way.</description></item><item><title>beepify.io source code available</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/beepify-io-source-code-available/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 22:21:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/beepify-io-source-code-available/</guid><description>All the source code from the beepify posts is available at: https://github.com/hamilton-lima/beepify-server-playframework See the related posts:
beepify.io, server side - part 1 beepify.io, server side - part 2</description></item><item><title>Increase Ant Hibernate Junit tests Performance by 80%</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/increase-ant-hibernate-junit-tests-performance-by-80/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 20:52:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/increase-ant-hibernate-junit-tests-performance-by-80/</guid><description>If don´t want to read everything, just set forkingmode=&amp;ldquo;once&amp;rdquo; to have huge improvement in your tests processing time. :)
Now the details&amp;hellip; I have several, around 100 junit tests in Robolucha project, most of then use Hibernate and are run by an ant script. When you start Java Virtual machine Hibernate prepares itself to connect to the database by checking the necessary tables and preparing all the internals needed to work, but this process takes some time, some seconds to say the true.</description></item><item><title>Holidays selfhackaton - the start</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/holidays-selfhackaton-the-start/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2016 15:46:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/holidays-selfhackaton-the-start/</guid><description>[caption id=&amp;ldquo;attachment_110&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;800&amp;rdquo;]The selfhackaton plan![/caption] During this holidays celebration week, I will join myself in a hackaton! Me myself and I will code several new features to Robolucha. The image above shows the sprint meeting board, when my stakeholder, a.k.a. wife forced me to define priorities and a clear order of what to deliver during this week :) Translating the characters above for something more understandable, here is the list:</description></item><item><title>Manage your machine with Jenkins</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/manage-your-machine-with-jenkins/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 19:40:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/manage-your-machine-with-jenkins/</guid><description>On these days when Zuckberg is feeling like iron man, @see building Jarvis, I want to share a more modest automation :) Manage your machine with Jenkins the powerfull build tool. Jenkins was created to automate builds and any sort of workflows after developers send their code to the server, so it&amp;rsquo;s able to automate virtually anything, and that what I did used it on my own machine to automate some tasks:</description></item><item><title>Robolucha mask editor</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/robolucha-mask-editor/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 22:35:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/robolucha-mask-editor/</guid><description>Today Robolucha was updated including the mask editor, where you can customize your luchador mask, and see it in the arena! You can change colors and forms for several different layers, give a try and show your creativity with new cool masks for your luchador. Try the new mask editor here: http://ring.robolucha.com If you don´t know robolucha, it is a fantastic game I created where you can code your &amp;ldquo;luchadores&amp;rdquo; using javascript and battle in an arena with your friends.</description></item><item><title>Avoid murphy with Amazon S3</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-murphy-with-amazon-s3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 02:21:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-murphy-with-amazon-s3/</guid><description>Backups are like life insurance, you allways will be sorry if you don´t have when you need it. That&amp;rsquo;s why I am sharing this step by step way to backup your application or site or wherever you have in production.
Preparing the vault, a.k.a. Amazon S3 I decided to store my backups on Amazon S3 service, because is cheap, around USD0,03 per GB, and very simple to store and to retrieve the data.</description></item></channel></rss>