<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>automation on Hamilton Lima</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/tags/automation/</link><description>Recent content in automation on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hamiltonlima.com/tags/automation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Automating Grocery Lists with AI and LilArmy Scripts</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/automating-grocery-lists-with-ai-and-lilarmy-scripts/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/automating-grocery-lists-with-ai-and-lilarmy-scripts/</guid><description>My Friend Deepesh Mehta asked me to build a feature in lilarmy that he could use to manage his pantry inventory. My first reaction was &amp;ldquo;Oh let&amp;rsquo;s do some agent for that!&amp;rdquo; I guess I am AI bias like everybody else&amp;hellip; but after a little bit of reflection, and some conversation with Claudio and Blue, yeah I named my agents, Claudio is actually Claude Code and Blue a OpenClaw that I talk using Telegram&amp;hellip; But after the conversation I realized that what my friend needs is a deterministic behaviour: Define the expected state of the inventory, gather information of the current state and list what is missing, a.</description></item><item><title>AI Tools in Practice: From Potato Farming to Code Enhancement</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/ai-tools-in-practice-from-potato-farming-to-code-enhancement/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/ai-tools-in-practice-from-potato-farming-to-code-enhancement/</guid><description>In late 2022, when ChatGPT was launched, I remember joking with my colleagues that we should learn how to cultivate potatoes and beets because we&amp;rsquo;d soon be out of jobs. AI would do everything for us, right? Maybe that would be a future concern, something for generations down the road—it&amp;rsquo;s hard to predict what&amp;rsquo;s going to happen.
I know there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of concern about implementing proper safeguards, preventing AI from taking control, and managing how it will change our jobs.</description></item><item><title>Confirm new user email with Cypress and MailHog</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 09:09:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</guid><description>I really like Cypress, The tool is interactive, very developer friendly even if you don&amp;rsquo;t plan to have a fully automated test suite, it really can save time automating tasks like, fill some forms, repeat some tasks, reproduce bugs, create new users&amp;hellip; create new USERS&amp;hellip; oh wait CREATE NEW USERS, how on earth I will validate the user email?
So many options There are some posssibilities
Pay some email API services, oh GMAIL why you don&amp;rsquo;t have it?</description></item><item><title>Manage your machine with Jenkins</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/manage-your-machine-with-jenkins/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 19:40:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/manage-your-machine-with-jenkins/</guid><description>On these days when Zuckberg is feeling like iron man, @see building Jarvis, I want to share a more modest automation :) Manage your machine with Jenkins the powerfull build tool. Jenkins was created to automate builds and any sort of workflows after developers send their code to the server, so it&amp;rsquo;s able to automate virtually anything, and that what I did used it on my own machine to automate some tasks:</description></item><item><title>Closing github issues on commit</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/closing-github-issues-on-commit/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 19:13:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/closing-github-issues-on-commit/</guid><description>There is no better place to keep track of opensource projects issues, than the issues page at github :) like this one: https://github.com/hamilton-lima/vanhackaton-video-editor/issues And as expected there is an automated way to close the issues with comments from your commit messages. You can use several key words for that as github documentation explains here: https://help.github.com/articles/closing-issues-via-commit-messages/, can be: close, closes, closed, fix, fixes, fixed, resolve, resolves, resolved. To fix #4 &amp;amp; #6 I used the following commit message:</description></item></channel></rss>