<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>vanhackaton on Hamilton Lima</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/tags/vanhackaton/</link><description>Recent content in vanhackaton on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 14:03:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://hamiltonlima.com/tags/vanhackaton/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Best project for the challenge at vanhackathon</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/best-project-for-the-challenge-at-vanhackathon/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 14:03:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/best-project-for-the-challenge-at-vanhackathon/</guid><description>Last Friday night, I got one of the best news in weeks, my video-editor project was choosen as the Best project for the challenge: Choose your Own Adventure Video Builder! It feels very good when you see a great technical team from www.thinkific.com recognizing your effort and results, thanks for the good news Nick Schwinghamer, thanks for the Vanhackathon organization Ilya Brotzky!</description></item><item><title>Vanhackton - Lessons Learned</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-lessons-learned/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 23:00:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-lessons-learned/</guid><description>After a very intense weekend I feel like coming from the battle :) But it feels very good to deliver a good result in such a small timeframe. On this post I will describe some lessons learned from the past weekend and some decisions I made that worth.
POC - the start For every project, I allways plan for proof of concepts, small implementations that isolate the implementation complexity by implementing just the necessary, to solve one problem.</description></item><item><title>Vanhackton final submission</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-final-submission/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 22:03:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-final-submission/</guid><description>Final submission!!! last minutes!!!</description></item><item><title>Vanhackaton status 2</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-status-2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:38:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-status-2/</guid><description>Today was a very productive day!! tons of nice features add to the editor:
Converted all the javascript code to run inside an Angular application Create the UI to edit the questions, with add and remove Created the timeline that shows each question position in the video Created backend using node.js and SQLLite Add inline edit to the story title and questions Scroll to the question when clicks on the timeline marker Monitor the execution of the video and pause for the question, tracking the answer in the edit mode Getting close to the first usable version!</description></item><item><title>Vanhackaton food &amp; desktop</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-food-desktop/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 11:24:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-food-desktop/</guid><description>There is tradition that I learn at LudumDare, publish pictures of your food and desktop while in the hackaton!</description></item><item><title>Vanhackton status 1</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-status-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 11:20:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackton-status-1/</guid><description>First proof of concept is done! I choose the challenge to build and interactive video editor that will creae layers over existing videos, nice challenge btw :) Technical details that are in this status:
Load video player on the fly Add and remove questions layer over the video Pause and Play the video Forward the video x amount of seconds Monitor what is the current position of the video Now its time for next steps:</description></item><item><title>Vanhackaton is about to start</title><link>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-is-about-to-start/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 20:42:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://hamiltonlima.com/posts/vanhackaton-is-about-to-start/</guid><description>Vanhackaton is about to start, get ready!!</description></item></channel></rss>