<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Hamilton Lima</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 04:33:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Developer happiness, are we missing something?</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/developer-happiness-are-we-missing-something/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 04:33:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/developer-happiness-are-we-missing-something/</guid><description>Looking at Stack Overflow&amp;rsquo;s 2024 Developer Survey, specifically the question about job satisfaction, we see a pretty sad story: roughly 80% of developers are either unhappy or just complacent at work. Think about that - only 2 out of 10 professional developers actually enjoy what they&amp;rsquo;re doing.
This feels really wrong. When you look at the factors that contribute to happiness and unhappiness at work, about 50% relates to things like improving code quality, learning new technologies, building environments, or working on architecture.</description></item><item><title>AI Tools in Practice: From Potato Farming to Code Enhancement</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/ai-tools-in-practice-from-potato-farming-to-code-enhancement/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/ai-tools-in-practice-from-potato-farming-to-code-enhancement/</guid><description>In late 2022, when ChatGPT was launched, I remember joking with my colleagues that we should learn how to cultivate potatoes and beets because we&amp;rsquo;d soon be out of jobs. AI would do everything for us, right? Maybe that would be a future concern, something for generations down the road—it&amp;rsquo;s hard to predict what&amp;rsquo;s going to happen.
I know there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of concern about implementing proper safeguards, preventing AI from taking control, and managing how it will change our jobs.</description></item><item><title>Guiding Principles for Cleaner Code: YAGNI, KISS, SOLID, and Beyond</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/guiding-principles-for-cleaner-code-yagni-kiss-solid-and-beyond/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 12:56:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/guiding-principles-for-cleaner-code-yagni-kiss-solid-and-beyond/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Any fool can write code that a computer can understand. Good programmers write code that humans can understand.&amp;rdquo; - Martin Fowler source
When you start your coding journey, the natural instinct is to write instructions as if you&amp;rsquo;re talking to a person: &amp;ldquo;Hey computer, grab some eggs, butter, and flour, and let&amp;rsquo;s bake a cake.&amp;rdquo; Procedural it is—instruction after instruction, right? It seems easy to understand, but it’s actually not 😊.</description></item><item><title>Exploring NestJS: A Personal Journey and Key Insights</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/exploring-nestjs-a-personal-journey-and-key-insights/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 21:31:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/exploring-nestjs-a-personal-journey-and-key-insights/</guid><description>Time flies! It feels like just yesterday when Qi Chen introduced NestJS as our backend technology at Mindbeacon back in 2019. It was a perfect match for Angular—similar coding styles, dependency injection, plenty of decorators, and loads of CLI options. Today, NestJS (not to be confused with its cousin, Next.js) can do so much more: scheduling, support for RabbitMQ, Kafka, Redis, WebSockets, and the list goes on.
I might be a bit biased, having used it for the past five years, but sometimes it feels like I&amp;rsquo;ve not just used it—I&amp;rsquo;ve pushed it to its limits!</description></item><item><title>A love letter to ourselves</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/love-letter-to-ourselves/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/love-letter-to-ourselves/</guid><description>In the fast-paced world we live in, stress often feels like an unwelcome companion. But what if we had a tool to navigate through it? A process can serve as just that—an anchor in the storm, a love letter from our rational self to our stressed self.
A well-defined process is like having a map. It reduces decision fatigue by laying out clear steps, helping us focus on one task at a time.</description></item><item><title>Final Research Result on Fork Placement Interpretation</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/fork_placement_research/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/fork_placement_research/</guid><description>Final Research Result on Fork Placement Interpretation Research Description: A kitchen dispute arose where RL claimed that a fork placed on the side of the sink, with the tines pointing inward, signifies that it is still in use and should not be washed. On the other hand, HL disagreed, interpreting the fork as ready to be washed. This research aimed to gather community insights and opinions to help settle the disagreement by exploring how people interpret the positioning of a fork in this manner.</description></item><item><title>Daily Standups with a Twist: Ideas to Encourage Team Autonomy</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 01:47:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</guid><description>We are social animals and want to be part of a tribe, feel accepted, useful, and so on. Combine that with the fact that working remotely is incredibly convenient and productive—there&amp;rsquo;s no commuting downtime. (By the way, I’m not talking to those of you who join meetings while driving. Please don&amp;rsquo;t do that!) So, how do we achieve collaboration and a sense of belonging in a remote setting? I don&amp;rsquo;t have all the answers, but I can share some of the experiences and lessons we learned while building Playspace.</description></item><item><title>Happy blue t-shirt day</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/happy-blue-tshirt-day/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 08:51:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/happy-blue-tshirt-day/</guid><description>During the craziness of COVID, many people started visiting places in their minds where, as a Theologist, I already enjoy frequent flyer status. These are not all dark places; there are certainly gray ones, and a few dark places as well. Mostly, they are places inside your head with dust and very low circulation. I am talking about questions on life and death, the meaning of our existence, and similar questions that are not usually part of lunch talk.</description></item><item><title>Confirm new user email with Cypress and MailHog</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 09:09:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/confirm-new-user-email-with-cypress-and-mailhog/</guid><description>I really like Cypress, The tool is interactive, very developer friendly even if you don&amp;rsquo;t plan to have a fully automated test suite, it really can save time automating tasks like, fill some forms, repeat some tasks, reproduce bugs, create new users&amp;hellip; create new USERS&amp;hellip; oh wait CREATE NEW USERS, how on earth I will validate the user email?
So many options There are some posssibilities
Pay some email API services, oh GMAIL why you don&amp;rsquo;t have it?</description></item><item><title>Avoid insanity when handling errors with Chai</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-insanity-when-handling-errors-with-chai/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jul 2021 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/avoid-insanity-when-handling-errors-with-chai/</guid><description>If you ever played Farcry3 for sure you will remember the guy in the picture, if you never hear about him, Take a look on this video, The definition of insanity - Far Cry 3.
While coding some unit tests for the SmallFlatWorld server, I got myself in a very interesting situation, where my old Java memories guided me to implement a test in a specific way, while some documentation was pointing in another direction&amp;hellip; Well Vaas has a point, repeating the same thing over and over and expecting the same results it&amp;rsquo;s kinda insane.</description></item></channel></rss>