<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>scrum on Hamilton Lima</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/tags/scrum/</link><description>Recent content in scrum on Hamilton Lima</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 21:42:42 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hamiltonlima.com/tags/scrum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>WIP-ONE: Your Focus Superpower</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/wip-one-your-focus-superpower/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 21:42:42 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/wip-one-your-focus-superpower/</guid><description>Ever feel like your brain is being pulled in a dozen different directions? You&amp;rsquo;re juggling browser tabs, conversations, and a to-do list that never seems to shrink. If you feel scattered and unproductive, there&amp;rsquo;s a simple concept that can help you get back on track. It&amp;rsquo;s called WIP-ONE, and it&amp;rsquo;s your key to getting more done with less stress.
WIP stands for &amp;ldquo;Work in Progress,&amp;rdquo; and WIP-ONE means having only one task in progress at a time.</description></item><item><title>Daily Standups with a Twist: Ideas to Encourage Team Autonomy</title><link>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 01:47:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hamiltonlima.com/posts/daily-standups-with-a-twist-ideas-to-encourage-team-autonomy/</guid><description>We are social animals and want to be part of a tribe, feel accepted, useful, and so on. Combine that with the fact that working remotely is incredibly convenient and productive—there&amp;rsquo;s no commuting downtime. (By the way, I’m not talking to those of you who join meetings while driving. Please don&amp;rsquo;t do that!) So, how do we achieve collaboration and a sense of belonging in a remote setting? I don&amp;rsquo;t have all the answers, but I can share some of the experiences and lessons we learned while building Playspace.</description></item></channel></rss>